Guide to the Homevale Garden Club (Missoula, Mont.) Records 1949-1988
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Homevale Garden Club (Missoula, Mont.) Records
1949-1988
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 193
Homevale Garden Club (Missoula, Mont.)
3.5 linear feet
The Homevale Garden Club in Missoula, Montana, was an organization that shared gardening knowledge and promoted pest control, garden shows, and military memorials. The collection includes clippings, financial records, correspondence, meeting minutes, organizational information, photographs, publications, and scrapbooks.
Historical Note
The Homevale Garden Club in Missoula, Montana, became a member of the Federation of Garden Clubs on January 28, 1949. The first elected president was Mrs. R.S. McLaughin; Mrs. Verne Osborne, Vice President; and Mrs. Shryock, Secretary/Treasurer. The club chose the climbing red rose for its flower. The garden club accomplished many deeds during its forty-one years of service, specifically working to beautify the community. The Federation planned the Blue Star Memorial Highway through Missoula to honor the men and women who served in the Armed Forces of WWII. Homevale joined with other garden clubs to have the first flower show in Missoula, a show which portrayed the United Nations theme of peace and goodwill. The club won a Blue Ribbon for its junior Garden Club work. The Federation of Montana won a national award for pest control. The club motto was "Do something for others when and wherever you can" and "more intelligent, more inspired gardening." Members taught children to appreciate nature and to see the importance of conservation. The club was on the honor role annually for the Federation of Garden Clubs. The Homevale Garden Club disbanded in 1988.
The collection includes clippings, financial records, correspondence, meeting minutes, organizational information, photographs, garden club publications, and scrapbooks from 1949 to 1988 for the Homevale Garden Club. The collection also includes information the Montana Federation of Garden Clubs, in which Homevale was a member. Homevale sponsored a junior garden club for youths and also sponsored many Missoula area beautification projects, many of which are chronicled in the scrapbooks.
The collection is divided into eight series:
Series I: Clippings, 1 folder, 1965-1971
Series II: Financial Records, 1 folder, 1959-1971
Series III: General Correspondence, 1 folder, 1958-1985
Series IV: Minutes, 3 folders, 1959-1988
Series V: Organization, 7 folders, 1949-1980
Series VI: Photographs, 10 photos, 1949-1985
Series VII: Publications, 1 folder, 1952-1968
Series VIII: Scrapbooks, 14 volumes, 1949-1968
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
Gift of the Homevale Garden Club, 1990, and Lillian Hornick, 1991.
During reprocessing all photographs were removed from dispersed folders, designated as a separate series, and transferred to the Archives general photograph collection.
Gardening--Montana--Missoula--Societies, etc.; Gardening for teenagers--Montana--Missoula; Urban beautification--Montana--Missoula; Women--Montana--Missoula--Societies and clubs
Missoula (Mont.)--Social life and customs
Montana Federation of Garden Clubs
Scrapbooks; Photographs
Montana; Photographs; Scrapbooks; City and Town Life; Women
- Clippings, 1965-1971; Series I; 1 folder
  This series contains newspaper clippings about garden clubs, Homevale Garden Club, and two women associated with the club. One article deals with the Western Montana Fair and asking groups and people not to forget about the fair deadline. The two articles on members of the Homevale club are Mrs. Ray Nelson and former club president, Lillian Hornick.
  The series is arranged chronologically.
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1965, 1968, 1971, undated (Box-folder 1/1)
- Financial Records, 1959-1971; Series II; 1 folder
  The series contains check stubs, receipts, bank notices, and canceled checks for the Homevale Garden Club.
  - Check stubs, receipts, band notices, and canceled checks, 1959-1971 (Box-folder 1/2)
- General Correspondence, 1958-1985; Series III; 1 folder
  The series contains cards and letters to the membership of the garden club. Two letters of appreciation are also included; one was written to the Sears Foundation for a $35.00 grant for a beautification project, and the other is written to a Mrs. Lovell for sending a donation of $5.00 to buy 4H dresses for the junior garden club.
  - Two Cards and Letters, 1958, 1963, 1968, 1985 (Box-folder 1/3)
- Minutes, 1959-1988; Series IV; 3 folders
  This series contains the meeting minutes for the monthly meetings of the club. This series documents the activities of the Homevale Garden Club and its members. Also included in the minutes are monthly financial reports. Newspaper clippings associated with each month's activities of the club is included in the month's minutes.
  - Meeting Minutes, 1959-1964 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1968-1978 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1979-1988 (Box-folder 1/6)
- Organization, 1949-1980; Series V; 7 folders
  This series contains a history of the Homevale Garden Club written in 1979. It also consists of applications for the Montana Federation of Garden Clubs Awards and the corresponding awards given. The series also contains programs from flower shows and the awards that the members of the club were given.
  The series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Applications for State Awards, 1969 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Awards, 1969 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - History of Homevale Garden Club, 1979 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Homevale Garden Club First Annual Placement Show, 1960 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Membership, 1980 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Missoula's First Annual Flower Show Wrap-Up, 1949 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Yearly Program, 1969 (Box-folder 1/13)
- Photographs, 1949-1985; Series VI; 10 photographs
  This series consists of photographs from the garden club's activities. They depict work on a beautification project, a dinner banquet, and group photos.
  - Beautification Project, undated; 99-1000
  - Beautification Project, undated; 99-1001
  - Beautification Project, undated; 99-1002
  - Group Photo, undated; 99-1003
  - Dinner Group Photo, 25 Feb, 1985; 99-1004
  - 4H Kitchen Queens, Sponsored by Homevale Garden Club, 1968-1969; 99-1005
  - Group Photo, undated; 99-1006
  - Group Photo, undated; 99-1007
  - Group Photo, undated; 99-1008
  - Main Room of Missoula's First Annual Flower Show, 1949; 99-1009
  - Negative, Group Photo, undated; 99-1010
- Publications, 1952-1968; Series VII; 1 folder
  This series consists of booklets from other sources dealing with garden clubs. The booklets are Progress through Perfectly Planned Programs for Garden Clubs, Handbook of the Montana Federation of Garden Clubs, By-Laws and Awards for Montana Federation of Garden Clubs, The Role of the Garden Club in Community Beautification. Another booklet that is in the series is a dictionary on plant names. Also in the series a diagram sheet on how to build a bird house, a past garden club project.
  - Bird House Diagram, undated (Box-folder 1/14)
  - By-Laws and Awards, Montana Federation of Garden Clubs, 1963
  - Handbook of the Montana Federation of Garden Clubs, 1952
  - The Home Garden Self-Pronouncing Dictionary of Plant Names, 1948
  - Montana Federation of Garden Clubs Annual Board Meeting Agenda, 1968
  - Progress through Perfectly Planned Programs for Garden Clubs, undated
  - The Role of the Garden Club in Community Beautification, 1964
- Scrapbooks, 1949-1968; Series VIII; 14 volumes
  This series consists of 14 scrapbooks made by the Homevale Garden Club. In these scrapbooks are newspaper clippings, membership certificates, annual programs, pictures of flowers and people, and newsletters. Project announcements, award ribbons, meeting minutes, and correspondence are also in the books. Two books in the series are dedicated to specific events, the Special Achievement Award and the Civic Development Project.
  - 1949-1952 (Box-volume OS1/1)
  - 1952-1957 (Box-volume OS1/2)
  - 1954-1959 (Box-volume OS2/3)
  - 1958-1959 (Box-volume OS2/4)
  - 1959-1962 (Box-volume OS3/5)
  - 1960-1964 (Box-volume OS4/6)
  - 1962-1966 (Box-volume OS5/7)
  - 1964-1967 (Box-volume OS6/8)
  - 1965-1967 (Box-volume OS6/9)
  - 1967 (Box-volume OS7/10)
  - Special Achievement Award, 1967 (Box-volume OS8/11)
  - 1967-1968 (Box-volume OS8/12)
  - 1949-1968 (Box-volume OS8/13)
  - Civic Development Project, 1963-1968 (Box-volume OS8/14)